Guide to the Kenyon Family Papers, 1893-1972 CTC.1973.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Kenyon Family Papers
1893-1972
1909-1950
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Kenyon family
CTC.1973.01
5 Linear Feet (10 boxes)
The Kenyon family operated the Kenyon Theatre, the first "high class" vaudeville theatre on Pittsburgh's Northside. They later opened the Kenyon Opera House, also known as the Pitt Theatre, in downtown Pittsburgh. Elmer Bernard Kenyon was the head of Carnegie Institute of Technology's Drama Department, was a press agent for many prominent actors, and founded the Pittsburgh Drama League. This collection contains autographed photos, theatre records, correspondence, clippings, vaudeville reviews, etc.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Professor Stanley Goodman, an executor of the T. Thomas Kenyon Estate, 1973. Additional items were donated by the Van Wissink family in 1977 and Professor Stanley Goodman on November 16, 1979.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains the business and personal records of Thomas Kenyon and his two sons, Elmer Bernard and Titus Thomas. The majority of this collection pertains to Elmer Bernard Kenyon. For the most part the collection is comprised of paper records from the first half of the twentieth century. The collection is organized into twelve series.
Biography
The Kenyon family was closely associated with theatre in Pittsburgh for twenty years (1909-1929), maintaining a less direct involvement with local theatre for many years afterwards. Elmer Kenyon, the elder of the two brothers, was associated with the national theatre scene as well.
Thomas Kenyon, the father, emigrated from Ireland and eventually settled in Allegheny City where he operated a dry goods store on Federal Street. On that site he built the Kenyon Theatre in 1909 as the first "high class" theatre on the Northside. Three years later he opened the first Kenyon Opera House, also a vaudeville theatre, in downtown Pittsburgh, on Penn Avenue near Seventh. Because of labor problems and illness, he soon withdrew from active participation in his theatres, and in 1919 he sold his interests.
Both theatres have since been demolished. The Kenyon Theatre remained standing for more than fifty years, until the raising of the Northside area required for Allegheny Center. The Kenyon Opera House achieved a decade of splendor as the Pitt Theatre, one of the city's major legitimate playhouses, after the Shuberts took over in 1919. When its auditorium was torn down in 1951 it was the Barry; the façade lasted until 1963.
The major portion of personal papers in this collection pertains to Elmer Bernard Kenyon, 1886-1949. After he received his degree from Harvard in 1913 he taught first at St. Viator College near Chicago, and then, 1916-29, taught English at Pittsburgh's new Schenley High School. After a brief association with the Theatre Guild he became head of Carnegie Institute of Technology's Drama Department, in 1931. In 1936 he returned to the Theatre Guild, and was press agent for Maurice Evans, Judith Anderson, and Helen Hayes, among others. Mr. Kenyon founded the Pittsburgh Drama League, was its president and edited its Review for many years, and was a director of the national organization. He was also a popular lecturer in Pittsburgh, and contributed to various national journals. He retired in 1947, and in 1949 he died, survived briefly by his mother, and by his brother, Titus Thomas.
T. Thomas Kenyon, 1892-1973, had assumed increasing responsibility at the Northside Theatre and was its manager for several years before the theatre was sold. He also managed the Pitt Theatre during its most glamorous period, 1923-29. He lived alone in Pittsburgh from the time of his mother's death in 1949, presumably managing his business interests, until his own death in 1973. There were no survivors and he left $1.2 million to the Catholic Diocese of Pittsburgh.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into twelve series:
Series I. Biographical Information, 1949-1973
Series II. Correspondence, 1893-1972
Series III. Notes and School Papers
Series IV. Scrapbooks
Series V. Theatre Guild Press Releases
Series VI. Lectures and Publications
Series VII. Newspaper Clippings, 1901-1969
Series VIII. Miscellany, 1910-1935
Series IX. Theatre Records, 1909-1940
Series X. Photographs, 1921-1941
Series XI. Phonorecords
Series XII. Oversize Materials
Previous Citation
Kenyon Family Papers, 1893-1972, CTC.1973.01, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Kenyon Family Papers, 1893-1972, CTC.10, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
Pitt Theatre Programs, Ford E. and Harriet R. Curtis Theatre Collection of Pittsburgh Theatre Programs, 1840-present, CTC.1966.01, Curtis Theatre Collection, Archives & Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Pittsburgh Drama League, Curtis Theatre Collection, Archives & Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Phonograph records; Drama League review; Theatrical managers -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Teachers -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Theater -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Performing arts -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Intellectual life; North Side (Pittsburgh, Pa.) -- Intellectual life; Correspondence; Theater; Scrapbooks; Press releases; Lectures; Clippings (Information artifacts); Photographs; Kenyon family; Pittsburgh Drama League (Pa.); Theatre Guild; Kenyon, Elmer B. (Elmer Bernard); Kenyon, T. Thomas (Titus Thomas)
- Biographical Information, 1949-1973; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Includes Elmer Kenyon's autobiographical notes written for the Theatre Guild and obituaries of Elmer Kenyon and T. Thomas Kenyon.
  - Elmer Kenyon autobiography furnished for the Theatre Guild - carbon typescript (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Elmer Kenyon - obituaries and Harvard records clippings, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Titus Thomas Kenyon - obituaries, March 1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1893-1972; II.
  Primarily, this series is personal correspondence, with some business correspondence included, both to and from the Kenyons. It is broken into five subseries. Included are typed letters signed, autograph letters, and carbon copies of letters. Signed letters (some TLS, but most ALS) are from Maurice Evans, Minnie Maddern Fiske, the Sotherns, Helen Hayes, Lucille Laverne, and others, many of the theatre celebrities also represented in the photograph series. One group of letters, from William Moore Patch, relates to his trial in Philadelphia. Another group refers to T. Thomas Kenyon's gift of Elmer Kenyon's Papers to the New York Public Library. Business correspondence includes one folder of lectures to and from Warren Munsell, Business Manager of the Theatre Guild, and another folder contains correspondence with the Shuberts.
  - Thomas Kenyon, 1.
    - Thomas Kenyon, Sr. - to Mrs. Kenyon, 1893-1913 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Elmer Kenyon, 2.
    - Elmer Kenyon - New Year's greetings to his parents, 1895-1896 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Elmer Kenyon - World War I post cards to his mother, 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Elmer Kenyon - excerpts from World War I correspondence to his mother prepared by Titus Thomas for distribution to friends after Elmer's death, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Elmer Kenyon - from Maurice Evans, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Elmer Kenyon - from Minnie Maddern Fiske, 1924-1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Elmer Kenyon - Dorothy Jean Minnemeyer Van Wissink, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Elmer Kenyon - from E.H. Sothern and Julia Marlow, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Elmer Kenyon - miscellaneous, 1929-1948 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Elmer Kenyon and T. Thomas Kenyon, 3.
    - Elmer and Titus Thomas Kenyon - Harold V. Cohen, Jerone Volk, Karl Krug, Kaspar Monahan, 1932-1958 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Elmer and Titus Thomas Kenyon - from Helen Hayes, 1933-1949 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Elmer and Titus Thomas Kenyon - from Ray Henderson, 1932-1937 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Elmer and Titus Thomas Kenyon - Florence Fisher Parry, 1937-1949 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Elmer and Titus Thomas Kenyon - from Aug. Rottenbach, 1908-1911 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Elmer and Titus Thomas Kenyon - correspondence to newspapers, 1932-1964 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Elmer and Titus Thomas Kenyon - miscellaneous correspondence, 1910-1943 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - T. Thomas Kenyon, 4.
    - Titus Thomas Kenyon - to his mother, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Titus Thomas Kenyon - from Judith Anderson (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Titus Thomas Kenyon - Brooks Atkinson, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Titus Thomas Kenyon - from Katharine Cornell, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Titus Thomas Kenyon - John K Daly, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Titus Thomas Kenyon - from Anne Ford, 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Titus Thomas Kenyon - Sara Greenspan, 1937-1943 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Titus Thomas Kenyon - from Ann Harding, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Titus Thomas Kenyon - from Bill K., 1938-1968 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Titus Thomas Kenyon - Lucille Lacey, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Titus Thomas Kenyon - from Lucille LaVerne, 1924-1928 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Titus Thomas Kenyon - from Joan Marion, 1927-1949 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Titus Thomas Kenyon - Dorothy Jean Minnemeyer Van Wissink, 1950-1961 (Box 1, Folder 32-33)
    - Titus Thomas Kenyon - from Warren P. Munsell business manager of the Theatre Guild, 1934-1939 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Titus Thomas Kenyon - New York Public Library, 1949-1961 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Titus Thomas Kenyon - William Moore Patch, 1923-1930 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Titus Thomas Kenyon - J.J. Shubert and Lee Schubert, 1924-1928 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Titus Thomas Kenyon - from Cepha (Sisk?), 1934-1957 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Titus Thomas Kenyon - from Leo, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Titus Thomas Kenyon - miscellaneous letters received, 1910-1972 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Letters of Condolence, 5.
    - Letters and telegrams of condolence on the deaths of Elmer Kenyon and Mrs. Thomas Kenyon, 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Notes and School Papers, III.
  Contained in this series are a set of notebooks of Elmer Kenyon's dating back to when he was a student. It is unclear whether or not they date back to his time at Harvard. There is also one folder of miscellany that related to Elmer's time as a teacher at St. Viator College, Schenley High School, and Carnegie Tech. Note that none of the material in this series is dated.
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - English notebooks (Box 2, Volume 1-2)
  - History notebook (Box 2, Volume 3)
  - German notebook (Box 2, Volume 4)
  - Literature notebook (Box 2, Volume 5)
- Scrapbooks, IV.
  There are four scrapbooks that are contained in this series. Scrapbooks two and three are of particular interest for personal clippings and memorabilia, 1913-31. The second scrapbook with newspaper clippings, correspondence, programs, etc., from St. Viator college, Bourbonnais, Ill.; Schenley High School, Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh Drama League; etc. Includes clippings regarding Elmer Kenyon's lectures, several articles by him, programs from women's clubs at which he lectures in 1929, and various issues of Pittsburgh Drama League Review. This oversized scrapbook has been disbound and placed into folders. The fourth scrapbook, containing Elmer Kenyon's lecture programs to local women's clubs, 1929-36, has been dismantled and divided into four file folders.
  - Scrapbook 1 - Mounted clippings regarding literature, 1913–1915? (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 2 - Elmer Kenyon, 1913-1939 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 3 - Mounted clippings most regarding Elmer Kenyon, 1929-1931 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook 4 - Elmer Kenyon's lecture programs, 1929-1936 (Box 3, Folder 4-7)
- Theatre Guild Press Releases, V.
  This series contains press releases written by Elmer Kenyon, while working for the Theatre Guild. It includes materials on Hamlet, Macbeth, Twelfth night, Amphitryon 38, The cherry orchard, Harriet, The Philadelphia story, The skin or our teeth, and Wine of choice, Maurice Evans, Judith Anderson, Helen Hayes, the Lunts, Katharine Hepburn, Katharine Cornell, and Miriam Hopkins. These press releases are not typical publicity, but well written scholarly pieces.
  - the Cherry Orchard (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Hamlet - with Maurice Evans (Box 4, Folder 2-6)
  - Harriet - with Helen Hayes (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - the Lonely Way (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Amphitryon 38 and Idiot's Delight - with the Lunts (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Macbeth - with Maurice Evans and Judith Anderson (Box 4, Folder 10-14)
  - the Philadelphia Story - with Katharine Hepburn (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - the Skin of Our Teeth (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - the Three Sisters - with Katharine Cornell (Box 4, Folder 17-18)
  - Twelfth Night - with Helen Hayes and Maurice Evans (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Wine of Choice - with Miriam Hopkins (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Lectures and Publications, VI.
  This series includes journal articles, letters to the editor, and typescripts of Elmer Kenyon's. In addition to the theatre materials there is one lecture of Cardinal Newman, dated 1945.
  - Typescripts (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Published articles (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Pittsburgh Drama League miscellany (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1901-1969; VII.
  The newspaper clippings in this series contain mostly personal information on Elmer and T. Thomas Kenyon, the theatres, Elmer Kenyon's press releases, various newspaper columns, letters to the editor by the Kenyons, and clippings on various aspects of the theatre, including Pittsburgh's theatre history.
  - Newspaper articles and letters to the editor by Elmer Kenyon, 1911-1945 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Elmer Kenyon as Head of the Drama Department at the Carnegie Institute of Technology, 1931-1936 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Elmer Kenyon miscellaneous, 1932-1964 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Titus Thomas Kenyon, 1930-1962 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Kenyon Theatre - Northside, 1901-1961 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Kenyon Theatre and Kenyon Opera House - labor problems, 1913 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Pitt Theatre, 1912-1963 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Pittsburgh theatre history, 1934-1959 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Charles M. Bregg columns (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Charles M. Bregg columns on Henry Miller and letter from Elmer Kenyon (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Jackson D. Hogg columns (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - William Moore Patch columns (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - William M. Rimmel's columns on the Northside, 1958-1969 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Frank Patterson columns (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous letters to the editor. (Includes group by P.J. McCormick – pseud. for E.K? or marked for his attention?), 1941-1957 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Maurice Evans, 1926-1941 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Maurice Evans and Judith Anderson in Macbeth, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Helen Hays, 1941-1944 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Ray Henderson's death - Katharine Cornell's press agent (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Katharine Hepburn, 1939-1941 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Henry Irving (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Richard Mansfield (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Russian theatre: Moscow Art Theatre, Chekhov and others, 1920-1953 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - George Bernard Shaw, 1952-1956 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Theatre Guild and American Theatre Society, 1934-1945 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Theatre - miscellaneous, 1920-1963 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1914-1953 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Miscellany, 1910-1935; VIII.
  This small series includes some personal effects of the Kenyons. Of note are several Jack and W.B. Yeats prints, a notebook with poetry by Titus Thomas, and a lock of Elmer Kenyon's hair (presumably from when he was a child).
  - Elmer Kenyon - Harvard diploma, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Elmer Kenyon - miscellaneous memorabilia, 1910-1930 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Titus Thomas Kenyon - miscellaneous memorabilia, 1914-1935 (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
  - A history of Pittsburgh theatre by Miriam T. Malakoff, 1931 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Art prints (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Poetry, 1931-1935 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Sheet music (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Theatre Records, 1909-1940; IX.
  The Kenyon Theatre records are fairly complete, including programs, ledgers, and booking receipts, all 1909-1919. Of particular interest is T. Thomas Kenyon's small holograph notebook index of vaudeville companies with his personal evaluation of each. For the Pitt Theatre, there is Mr. Kenyon's "Obit," and a small notebook containing the financial record during the years under his management.
  - Kenyon Theatre Northside - programs, 1909-1914 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Kenyon Theatre Northside - programs, 1915-1916 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Kenyon Theatre Northside - programs, 1917 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Kenyon Theatre Northside - programs, 1918-1919 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Vaudeville acts - Titus Thomas Kenyon's evaluations, 1919 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Kenyon Theatre Northside - ledgers, 1910-1919 (Box 7, Volume 1-2)
  - Kenyon Theatre Northside - Vaudeville bookings receipts Polack Vaudeville Circuit, 1909-1912 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Kenyon Theatre Northside - Liberty Vaudeville Contracting Co., 1915-1919 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Kenyon Theatre Northside - miscellaneous, 1912-1915 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Pitt Theatre "Obit," by Thomas Titus Kenyon (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Pitt Theatre - 1st Program as Kenyon Opera House, 1912 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Pitt Theatre - Financial records, 1920-1929 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous theatre records, 1913-1940 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Photographs, 1921-1941; X.
  The Kenyons amassed a very impressive photograph collection of theatrical notables. Many of these photographs are signed. Family photographs include several of the elder Kenyons and of the brothers as both children and adults. The photographs are in alphabetical order.
  - Personal Photographs, 1.
    - Anne Ford (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Kenyon Theatre, Northside (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Elmer Kenyon (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Elmer and Titus Thomas Kenyon (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - E.K. and T.T.K. that were owned by Dorothy Jean Minnemeyer Van Wissink (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Mr. and Mrs. Thomas Kenyon (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Titus Thomas Kenyon (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Father Maguire (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Mrs. Robeson (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Mr. and Mrs. Rottenbach (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Unidentified (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Theatre Photographs, 1921-1941; 2.
    - Judith Anderson as Lavinia Mannon in Mourning becomes Electra - signed (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Margaret Anglin - signed (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Brooks Atkinson (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Tallulah Bankhead - signed (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Marjorie Barrett (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Rosemary Casey? (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Olga Chekhova and Ivan Moskvin - signed (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Katharine Cornell - signed (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Henrietta Corssman - signed (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Jane Cowl (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Maurice Evans - signed, 1940-41 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Ann Harding (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Helen Hayes - signed, 1925-1941 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Suzanne Keener as Peg in Peg O' My Dreams - signed (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Lucille La Verne as Widow Cagle in Sun-Up - signed (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Francie Larimore - signed (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Joan Marion (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Nazimova - signed (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Eugene O'Neill (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Catherine Dale Owen (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - Marga Schenk - signed (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - George Bernard Shaw (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - E.H. Sothern as Hamlet - signed, 1921 (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - Constantin Stanislavski - signed, 1924 (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - Sophie Stewart as Olivia - signed (Box 8, Folder 36)
    - John Van Druten - signed (Box 8, Folder 37)
    - Elizabeth Hester Ward (Box 8, Folder 38)
    - Unidentified (Box 8, Folder 39)
- Phonorecords, XI.
  - Elmer Kenyon interviewing Charles Hopkins - director of No More Ladies at the Pittsburgh Playhouse, 1935 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
  - Maurice Evans in the "England" speeches from Richard II and Henry V - the British War Relief Society Inc. (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Oversize Materials, XII.
  The majority of this series contains oversized photographs, many of which are autographed. Also of note is a phrenological chart of Elmer Kenyon from when he was only eight years old.
  - Judith Anderson and Florence Reed in Morning Becomes Elektra - signed oversized photograph (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Laine Blair - signed oversize photograph (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Ann Harding - oversized photograph (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Katherine Cornell - signed oversized photograph (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Helen Hayes as Portia in the Merchant of Venice - signed oversize photograph, 1939 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Helen Hayes - charcoal portrait by William Robert Shulgold, 1927 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Elmer Kenyon - oversized photograph (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Titus Thomas Kenyon - oversized photograph (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Alfred Lunt and Lynn Fontanne - signed oversized photograph (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Katherine MacDonald - signed oversized print (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Joan Marion in Gentlemen Prefer Blondes - signed oversized photograph (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Julia Marlowe - signed oversized photograph, 1921 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Eleanor Painter? - signed oversized photograph (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Phrenological chart of Elmer Kenyon, October 27, 1894 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - E.H. Southern - signed oversized photograph, 1917 (Box 10, Folder 15)